# Alexander Giovannelli

Phone: +1-740-258-9709Email: agiovannelli@vt.edu Site: https://agiovannelli.github.io/

## $\operatorname{Summary}$

My research interest lies in the intersections of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Augmented/Virtual Reality (AR/VR), and 3D User Interfaces (3DUI) for collaboration. I am exploring how to improve asynchronous collaborative processes using immersive technologies. Specifically, I am prototyping and evaluating systems that capture presenter actions, providing supplemental visuals and interactive mechanisms for observer playback.

## EDUCATION

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science advised by Doug A. Bowman, GPA: 4.00/4.00 Aug. 2021-Present

University of Cincinnati Cincinnati, OH, USA

B.S. in Computer Engineering with German Studies minor, GPA: 3.30/4.00 Aug. 2013-May 2018

# SKILLS

Programming Languages: C#, JavaScript, Java, Python, HTML, CSS

Productivity Tools: Unity, Git, JMP, SPSS, LaTeX, Tableau

## Research Experience

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA Spring 2023 & Fall 2023

Graduate Research Assistant

- Investigated methods for asynchronous and synchronous collaboration in immersive experiences
- Performed contextual inquiry and analysis to determine research goals
- Created prototype virtual reality applications using C# and Unity technologies

#### Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Livermore, CA, USA

Computing Research Intern

Summer 2023

- Developed guided tour prototypes for inspection processes in virtual reality using C# and Unity technologies
- Facilitated meetings between multi-disciplinary project stakeholders
- Prepared user study procedure for evaluation of prototype capabilities

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA Summer 2022

Graduate Research Assistant

- Conducted research regarding communication via avatars in augmented and virtual reality
- Generated prototype applications and experimental studies using C# and Unity technologies
- Designed and administered user studies in accordance with Institutional Review Board regulations

# Work Experience

#### JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Jul. 2018-Jul. 2021

Associate Software Engineer I

- Developed front-end features for Chase.com using JavaScript, HTML, and CSS technologies

Columbus, OH, USA

- Designed and implemented minimum viable product user interfaces via Figma design tool
- Authored technical documentation for product owners and developers
- Appointed subject matter expert in behavioral-driven development and CI/CD initiatives
- Automated logging of proprietary systems using the Python programming language

#### Siemens Healthineers

Forchheim, BY, DE

Software Engineer Intern

Jan. 2017-Aug. 2017

- Developed back-end software for use in advanced therapy devices using the C# programming language
- Created system architecture diagrams to record project design changes and behaviors
- Represented project team in international software integration meetings using German and English languages

#### Granville Exempted Village Schools

Granville, OH, USA

Systems Administrator Intern

May 2016-Jul. 2016

- Provisioned Windows and Linux server and workstation systems to support school network infrastructure
- Administered changes to proprietary devices regarding operating system applications, packages and images
- Managed summer technician team operations

#### Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2015–Dec. 2015

- Created full-stack internal software tools for engineers and project managers using C#, XML and SQL
- Updated existing project management software according to submitted user feedback
- Authored software usage documents to elaborate on internal tool usage

#### Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2014-Dec. 2014

- Enhanced existing proprietary software using the C# programming language
- Researched emerging technologies and presented potential process improvements for development team
- Coordinated project design changes with stakeholders

#### Publications

## Peer Reviewed Journal Papers

J1. A. Giovannelli, J. Thomas, L. Lane, F. Rodrigues and D. A. Bowman, "Gestures vs. Emojis: Comparing Non-Verbal Reaction Visualizations for Immersive Collaboration," in *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, vol. 29, no. 11, pp. 4772-4781, Nov. 2023, doi: 10.1109/TVCG.2023.3320254.

# Peer Reviewed Conference Papers

- C1. F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Pavanatto, H. Miao, J. C. d. Oliveira and D. A. Bowman, "AMP-IT and WISDOM: Improving 3D Manipulation for High-Precision Tasks in Virtual Reality," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 303-311, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR59233.2023.00045.
- C2. **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lisle, and D. A. Bowman, "Exploring the impact of visual information on intermittent typing in virtual reality", in 2022 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), 2022, pp. 8–17, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR55827.2022.00014.

# Peer Reviewed Workshops, Posters, Abstracts, & Contests

- W1. I. A. Tahmid, F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Lisle, J. Thomas and D. A. Bowman, "CoLT: Enhancing Collaborative Literature Review Tasks with Synchronous and Asynchronous Awareness Across the Reality-Virtuality Continuum," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality Adjunct (ISMAR-Adjunct), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 831-836, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR-Adjunct60411.2023.00183.
- W2. A. Giovannelli, F. Rodrigues, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, L. Lane, C. Connor, K. Davidson, G. N. Ramirez, B. David-John, and D. A. Bowman, "Clue hog: An immersive competitive lock-unlock experience using hook on go-go technique for authentication in the metaverse", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 945-946, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00315.
- W3. J. Thomas, S. W. Lee, **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lane, and D. Bowman, "A communication-focused framework for understanding immersive collaboration experiences", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 301–304, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00070.
- W4. L. Lisle, F. Lu, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, A. Giovannelli, C. Llo, L. Pavanatto, L. Zhang, L. Schlueter, and D. A. Bowman, "Clean the ocean: An immersive vr experience proposing new modifications to go-go and wim techniques", in 2022 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2022, pp. 920–921, doi: 10.1109/VRW55335.2022.00311.
- W5. E. Mohammadrezaei, A. Giovannelli, L. Lane, and D. Gračanin, "A digital twin based approach to smart lighting design", in 2022 Winter Simulation Conference (WSC), 2022.

## Projects

• Gesture-based 3DUI for Arithmetic Operations

Dec. 2023—Present

Design and prototyping of a virtual environment for embodied learning of arithmetic operations

• Guided Tours for Multiscale Collaborative Virtual Environments

Design and prototyping of a virtual environment for collaboration in multiscale inspection processes

• Surface Generation for MR Remote Collaboration Jun. 2022–Sept. 2023

Prototyping and testing of multi-user environment for shared surface creation and collaboration

#### AWARDS

• I/ITSEC Leonard P. Gollobin Scholarship	2023
• Davenport Leadership Fellowship	2023-2024
• Best Conference Paper Honorable Mention IEEE ISMAR 2022 [C2]	2022
• Best 3DUI Contest Entry [W4]	2022
• International Co-op Program Scholarship	2016 – 2017
• Matrix Technologies, Inc. Co-op Scholarship	2014 – 2016

## Professional Service

Student Volunteer
 Assist in event operations at IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality 2022
 Member of Computer Science Graduate Student Council
 Represent the interests of the CS graduate student body and assist in event planning
 Member of the Center for Human-Computer Interaction
 Active participant in the Center seminars regarding the study of human-computer interaction

# TEACHING

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Comparative Languages (CS-3304) Fall 2022

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Software Design & Data Structures (CS-2114) Fall 2021 & Spring 2022